{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "An expedition from this colony used the Good Hope in a futile expedition to reclaim a fur trading post on the Penobscot River. Much of the congregation of John Robinson immigrated to this colony from Leiden in the Netherlands. Myles Standish was a military leader of this colony, which was governed for nearly 30 years by William Bradford. Colonists from the Mayflower established, for ten points, what colony near a namesake rock in Massachusetts?",
      "answer": "Plymouth Colony"
    },
    {
      "question": "Descriptionacceptable.ThomasAquinascitedGenesis1:28[chapter1,verse28]asBiblicaljustification for this general action, so long as it was used as a means to divine happiness. The “spoilage” and “enough and as good” provisions limit the right to this practice, according to John Locke, who stated that this practice became legitimate through the mixing of labor. Rousseau’s Discourse on Inequality blames all the world’s “crimes, wars, and murders” on this practice, which takes place through enclosure of the commons. For ten points, name this practice that Locke sought to protect alongside life and liberty.",
      "answer": [
        "owning private property",
        "equivalents",
        "descriptions relating to buying property",
        "land, goods, things, etc. as substitutes for property",
        "the pursuit of property and similar phrases after “spoilage” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One ruler of this country, Fasilides, established a new capital at the city of Gondar. The Jesuit Pedro P´aez wrote a two volume history of this country, where the Oromo people migrated from south to north in the 16th century. This country is home to churches cut into the rock near the town of Lalibela. This country was ruled by members of the Solomonic Dynasty, like Zara Yaqob. For ten points, name this modern African country whose land was once ruled by the Kingdom of Axum on the Horn of Africa.",
      "answer": "Ethiopia"
    },
    {
      "question": "Darcus Howe was a civil rights leader in this country, where a race riot that inspired the Eddy Grant song “Electric Avenue” took place in Brixton. In 1968, a politician from this country delivered the controversial anti-immigration speech “Rivers of Blood.” In addition to Enoch Powell, another racist in this country was responsible for the murder of a member of its parliament, Jo Cox, in 2017. For ten points, name this European country that committed racial discrimination in Caribbean colonies like Jamaica and Barbados.",
      "answer": [
        "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland",
        "Great Britain",
        "England"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1886, Herman Presser and his group Lehr und Wehr Verein cited this amendment to challenge an Illinois law. This amendment’s jurisprudence favored the collective rights interpretation established in US v. Miller until the Roberts Court recently applied the individual rights doctrine in DC v. Heller and McDonald v. Chicago. For ten points, name this amendment that mentions a “well-regulated militia” and guarantees the right to bear arms.",
      "answer": "2nd Amendment to the U.S. Constitution"
    },
    {
      "question": "This foodstuff was first made from a plant called teosinte [tay-oh-sin-tay]. In 1885, Charles Cretors invented a machine to make this foodstuff, which he displayed at the 1893 Chicago World’s Fair. During World War II, sugar rations led to the tripling in consumption of this good, which the Redenbacher family started selling during the Great Depression. For ten points, name this food, a sweetened variety of which is found with peanuts in Cracker Jack, and which is the highest-selling food in American movie theaters.",
      "answer": "popcorn"
    },
    {
      "question": "This President introduced the ISF solidarity tax on wealth after running on the 110 Propositions platform. This man announced his country would give grants, not loans, to African nations in a speech at La Baule describing a “south wind” of democratization. This President, whose last meal was the illegal Ortolan bird, sunk the Greenpeace ship Rainbow Warrior and was forced to “cohabitate” with his rival Jacques Chirac. For ten points, name this first socialist President of France.",
      "answer": "Franc¸ois Mitterand"
    },
    {
      "question": "A primary source about life in this empire is provided by the letters of Lady Mary Wortley Montagu. The murdered miniaturist Elegant Effendi works under this empire in Orhan Pamuk’s novel My Name is Red. Cervantes’s left hand was badly maimed while fighting against this empire as part of the Spanish contingent at the Battle of Lepanto. For ten points, name this empire where authors were patronized by nobles in 19th century Bursa and Istanbul.",
      "answer": "Ottoman Empire"
    },
    {
      "question": "Thirty-six members of this country’s militia were killed in the Dawson massacre by Adrian Woll’s troops. At an inauguration ceremony in this country, the outgoing president spoke for three hours, so Algernon Thompson had to read the inaugural speech for the incoming president, Mirabeau Lamar. In this country, the “regulators” and “moderators” feuded over land rights and cattle rustling. For ten points, name this country whose first presidential election, held in 1836, was contested by Stephen Austin and Sam Houston.",
      "answer": "Republic of Texas"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this city, the Zelene Beretke and Patriotic League became infamous for firing on ambulances and UN employees. A massacre took place in the Markale market in this city, where Admira Ismic and Bosko Brkic became known as “Romeo and Juliet” after they were gunned down trying to cross Vrbanja [vir-bahn-yah] bridge. This city, the site of “Sniper Alley,” was besieged until 1996, after the signing of the Dayton Agreement. Republica Srpska besieged, for ten points, what capital city of Bosnia and Herzegovina?",
      "answer": "Sarajevo"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s most famous oration notes that “it is the young men who say yes or no” since “Looking Glass is dead.” This man, who allied with a small group from the Palouse tribe, was captured after a broken truce at the Battle of Bear Paw Mountain. This man declared that “my heart is sick and sad” and “I will fight no more forever” after his tribe was stopped by troops just miles south of the northern border. For ten points, name this chief of the Nez Perce who tried to lead his people to Canada.",
        "answer": "Chief Joseph"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Chief Joseph was captured by this man, the last to receive the rank of Commanding General in the American army. His other achievements include putting down the Pullman strike.",
        "answer": "Nelson Miles"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city includes the Vila Amaury attraction, an underwater village submerged in the artificial Lake Paranoa. Construction on this city began as the result of the “fifty years of progress in five” plan under Juscelino Kubitschek. It was built to take on the shape of an airplane by Lucio Costa. Oscar Niemeyer was commissioned to design this city as its government sought to move to a more central location from Rio de Janeiro. For ten points, name the capital of Brazil.",
        "answer": "Brasilia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The airplane shape of Brasilia was inspired by the work of what Swiss-French architect who designed the city of Chandigarh in the 1950s?",
        "answer": "Le Corbusier"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Legends about this site hold that it was originally built for Precha Ket Mealea. An early visitor to this site, Zhou Daguan, wrote that it was built in one night by a divine hand. This site features a mural of 92 asuras and 88 devas using the serpent Vasuki to churn the Sea of Milk. Though it was first built to honor Vishnu by Suryavarman II, this site was later rededicated to become a Buddhist place of worship. For ten points, name this temple complex constructed by the Khmer empire, a national symbol on the Cambodian flag.",
        "answer": "Angkor Wat"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Khmer civilization supported itself by using barays, including some built at Angkor Wat, to store water from this lake in Cambodia. This lake is the largest in Southeast Asia.",
        "answer": "Tonle Sap"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This process led to the martyring of the Bandiera Brothers. The Battle of Solferino helped accelerate this process by forcing Austria to cede land in the Treaty of Zu¨rich. This process spread to the southern regions with the Expedition of the Thousand. Count Cavour helped engineer this process alongside Giuseppe Garibaldi. For ten points, name this process which resulted in a new nation centered at Rome.",
        "answer": [
          "Italian unification",
          "the Risorgimento"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Italian unification was largely successful due to the efforts of this kingdom, led by Cavour for its king Victor Emmanuel II. It was named for an island and a region of northwestern Italy.",
        "answer": [
          "Kingdom of Sardinia-Piedmont",
          "either",
          "both underlined portions"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At this battle’s conclusion, William Washington had his horse shot out from under him as he tried to pursue the enemy commander. This battle’s losing side was misled into fighting by a report of an imminent attack on Fort Ninety-Six. The winning side in this battle deployed three defensive lines by the Broad River and resisted multiple assaults by the British Legion, leading Daniel Morgan’s men to eventually rout Banastre Tarleton’s forces. For ten points, name this 1781 battle of the Carolinas campaign that was fought on cattle grazing ground.",
        "answer": "Battle of Cowpens"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the Carolinas Campaign, the British were more successful in this 1780 battle in which Charles Cornwallis defeated Horatio Gates. Baron Johann de Kalb was killed in this battle.",
        "answer": "Battle of Camden"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This nation achieved recognition in the Twelve Years’ Truce, which was eventually broken when this nation was attacked by the Duke of Olivares. The Council of Blood was set up to quell insurrections in this nation by the Duke of Alba, who had been deployed by Philip II. The Peace of Westphalia formally ended this nation’s Eighty Years’ War with Spain and granted it its independence. For ten points, name this Low Country whose independence struggle was led by the House of Orange.",
        "answer": "The Netherlands or Holland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The resistance against the Spanish was led by this stadtholder from the House of Orange. He financed the Sea Beggars to attack Spanish shipping, but was assassinated by Balthasar Gerard.",
        "answer": "William the Silent or William I"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An inscription on this object bears the words “PASS AND STOW,” in honor of the two men who brought itback into use.A popular taleabout thisobjectholds thatits finaltask was theannouncement of John Marshall’s death. This object was first struck to mark the reading of the Declaration of Independence and has since received a two-foot-long crack on its side. For ten points, name this American landmark in Philadelphia that has not been rung in over a hundred years.",
        "answer": "Liberty Bell"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "When the British threatened to occupy Philadelphia in 1777, the Liberty Bell was transported to, and briefly held in, this Pennsylvania town. A 19th century steel company named for this town was once the second-largest steel company in the US, after Pittsburgh’s US Steel.",
        "answer": "Bethlehem Steel"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Agroupofartistsfromthiscountryknownas“Losgrandetres”[losgrand-aytrace]werecommissioned for murals in public buildings by Minister of Education Jos´e Vasconcelos. Jos´e Posada’s prints made in this country often feature calaveras or skeletons. Another artist from this country sparked outrage by including a portrait of Vladimir Lenin in his Man at the Crossroads. For ten points, name this country home to muralist Diego Rivera and his wife, Frida Kahlo.",
        "answer": "Mexico or the United Mexican States"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This French artist was inspired by Francisco Goya’s 3rd of May, 1808 to paint the execution of Mexico’s Emperor Maximilian.",
        "answer": "E´douard Manet"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "US Presidents Before They Were Presidents",
      "prompt": "Concerning pre-Presidential careers, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "President who served as a Five-Star General during World War II.",
          "answer": "Dwight D. Eisenhower"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who defeated Tenskwatawa [tensk-wah-ta-wah] at Tippecanoe and used the victory in his campaign slogan.",
          "answer": "William Henry Harrison"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who was a Governor of Arkansas and ran with a Tennessee Senator, Al Gore.",
          "answer": [
            "William Jefferson “Bill” Clinton",
            "William Jefferson Blythe"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Home state of Senator Warren Harding and Governor Rutherford B. Hayes.",
          "answer": "Ohio"
        },
        {
          "question": "Asian country where William Howard Taft served as governor-general from 1901 to 1903.",
          "answer": "The Philippines"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who helped write the Ostend Manifesto as Ambassador to Great Britain.",
          "answer": "James Buchanan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political boss who helped Harry Truman with a political machine based in Kansas City.",
          "answer": "Thomas Pendergast"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political group that dominated the New York legislature in the 1820s under Martin van Buren.",
          "answer": "Albany Regency"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Russia",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "“Terrible” tsar who killed his son and ruled Russia in the 16th century.",
          "answer": "Ivan the Terrible or Ivan IV"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religion followed by the traveler Ibn Fadlan, which the Rus briefly considered converting to before they found out it prohibited alcohol.",
          "answer": "Islam"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tsar who opened Russia to the west with a Grand Embassy in the late 17th century.",
          "answer": "Peter the Great or Peter I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nobleman who built fake villages to impress Catherine the Great and names a battleship whose men mutinied in 1905.",
          "answer": [
            "Grigory Potemkin",
            "Battleship Potemkin"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Viking chieftain who founded the Kievan Rus and names the dynasty before the Romanovs.",
          "answer": "Rurik"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mongol leader, the grandfather of Kublai Khan, who sent Subutai to attack the Kievan Rus in the 1220s.",
          "answer": [
            "Genghis Khan",
            "Chinggis Khan",
            "Temujin"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Mongol khan who, as the first leader of the Golden Horde, finished conquering Kievan Rus in 1237.",
          "answer": "Batu Khan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prince who defeated the Teutonic Knights at the Battle on the Ice at Lake Peipus.",
          "answer": "Alexander Nevsky"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "French Colonial History",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Founder of the Fifth Republic who gave Algeria its independence.",
          "answer": "Charles de Gaulle"
        },
        {
          "question": "Egyptian waterway targeted by France, Israel, and Great Britain in a 1956 Crisis.",
          "answer": [
            "Suez Canal",
            "Suez Crisis"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Colony whose independence movement was led by Ho Chi Minh.",
          "answer": "Vietnam or French Indochina"
        },
        {
          "question": "1954 battle in that colony in which France was defeated by Vo Nguyen Giap.",
          "answer": "Battle of Dien Bien Phu"
        },
        {
          "question": "Emperor who colonized Senegal and less successfully installed Maximilian I in Mexico.",
          "answer": "Napoleon III"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern African country that was formerly the French Upper Volta colony.",
          "answer": "Burkina Faso"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former French colony that faced a Tuareg rebellion aiming to establish the state of Azawad.",
          "answer": "Mali"
        },
        {
          "question": "Colonial border crisis in 1898 in which British and French troops stood off in Sudan.",
          "answer": "Fashoda incident or crisis, etc."
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1956, the leader of this organization wrote an open letter claiming that T.R.M. Howard’s “false charges” were “a disservice to common decency.” In 1971, a “Citizens’ Commission” used the broadcast of the Ali-Frazier “Fight of the Century” as a distraction to successfully raid one of this organization’s (20 pts)",
        "suburban offices in Media, Pennsylvania. That burglary recovered documents used by the Church Committee to declassify this organization’s (10 pts)",
        "COINTELPRO project, which illegally targeted activists like Martin Luther King, Jr. with illegal surveillance. For ten points, name this American law enforcement agency that was led for nearly 5 decades by J. Edgar Hoover."
      ],
      "answer": "Federal Bureau of Investigation or FBI"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Thomas Aquinas’s “Pange lingua” forms the basis of one of these pieces by Josquin des Prez [joh-skan dez prezz]. One of these compositions includes material originally written for the death of Augustus II and accession of Augustus III of Poland, and unusually calls one movement (20 pts)",
        "“Symbolum Nicenum.” Another of these works supposedly convinced the Council of Trent to not ban polyphony and was written for Pope (10 pts)",
        "Marcellus by Giovanni Palestrina. J.S. Bach wrote a B minor example of, for ten points, what type of sacred musical work that includes Credo and Kyrie movements and sets the weekly Catholic liturgy?"
      ],
      "answer": "masses"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One politician with this surname was the target of a foiled coup attempt, Operation Midnight Jackal, and her husband earned the label “Mr. Ten Percent” for receiving government kickbacks. Another leader with this surname declared that his country would obtain a (20 pts)",
        "nuclear weapon “even if we have to eat grass” and refused to recognize the Awami League; that politician was deposed by Zia al-Huq in Operation Fair Play. A woman with this surname was (10 pts)",
        "assassinated in 2008 by a suicide bomber while on the campaign trail. For ten points, name this surname held by two former prime ministers of Pakistan, Zulfikar and Benazir."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Bhutto family",
        "Benazir and/or Zulfikar Ali Bhutto"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Syagrius lost the Battle of Soissons [swah-sohn] to a ruler of these people, who also beat the Visigoths at the Battle of Vouill´e [VOO-ye]. Subgroups of these people included the Ripuarians and the Salians. After the Battle of Tertry, the (20 pts)",
        "Arnulfing Clan of these people grew power as Mayors of the Palace. A ruler of these people was crowned by Pope Leo III on Christmas Day. This group included the (10 pts)",
        "Merovingian Dynasty and its leaders included Pepin the Short and Clovis. Charlemagne was a leader of, for ten points, what Germanic group that eventually settled in Gaul?"
      ],
      "answer": "Franks"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) For designing one of these facilities, John Cockcroft and Ernest Walton won a Nobel Prize in 1951. After already spending 2 billion dollars, the development of one of these facilities named the SSC was canceled by (20 pts)",
        "Congress in 1993. Public safety concerns were raised after people thought one of these facilities built by CERN was capable of producing black (10 pts)",
        "holes. The Tevatron and the RHIC are examples of, for ten points, what scientific devices used to study physics at the atomic level, such as the Large Hadron Collider?"
      ],
      "answer": "particle accelerators"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man created a branch of philosophy inspired by Jan Jakob Maria de Groot called Universism. During the Great Depression, this defense minister sent troops to break the Menstad conflict, and as prime minister, he created the (20 pts)",
        "Hirden paramilitary. Following the German invasion of his country in Operation Weser Exercise, this man launched a coup via radio broadcast. This man was executed in (10 pts)",
        "Akershus Fortress in 1945 after he collaborated with the SS in the Holocaust. The Nasjonal Samling party was led by, for ten points, what infamous Norwegian traitor?"
      ],
      "answer": "Vidkun Quisling"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Description acceptable. One side in this war outnumbered the other eleven to seven in terms of massive military units called Akshauhini [ahk-shao-hee-nee]. In this war, (20 pts)",
        "Bhishma’s body was shot so full of arrows that he was disabled before his body touched the ground. A charioteer in this eighteen-day battle told his (10 pts)",
        "companion archer that he must not be afraid to face his family in single combat. The Kauravas faced off against the Pandavas in, for ten points, what war in which Krishna advises Arjuna in an Indian epic poem?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Kurukshetra War",
        "descriptions of the war or battle, etc. from the Mahabharata and/or the Bhagavad Gita",
        "the war between the Kauravas and Pandavas before “Kauravas” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Participants in this event were declared to be not culpable in a trial stemming from Plenty Horses’ assassination of Edward Casey. The day after this event, James Forsyth was attacked in the Bloody Pocket during the (20 pts)",
        "Drexel Mission Fight. This event, which took place on the Pine Ridge reservation, was partly a reaction to fears that Wovoka’s (10 pts)",
        "Ghost Dance movement might be a signal for an attack, though its immediate cause was Black Coyote’s refusal to hand over his rifle. For ten points, name this 1890 event in which more than 100 members of the Lakota tribe were massacred."
      ],
      "answer": "Wounded Knee massacre"
    }
  ]
}